Today is the day where we celebrate the change
of the axis of the Sun and that He moves
towards the tropic of cancer.
Tropic of cancer is the one
which represents the motherhood,
the motherhood of the Earth.
This tropic of Cancer has passed through
quite a big area of land
while the tropic of Capricorn has not.
And the area through which it has passed
it has created
different beautiful manifestation
of the motherhood qualities on this Earth.
We celebrate this change
because the Sun has now moved into the new
dimension so that all over the world
there will be the warmth of the Sun.
Warmth of the Sun
represents the warmth of God's love.
This is the reason why we celebrate
this festival
by giving you some sort of a sweet
made out of sesame seeds.
Sesame seeds are given because they are also heat giving
and now as we are coming from the cold,
we come to the hot season, in a way hotter season,
so to prepare you with that warmth of the Sun.
These special things are made out of the seed
of sesame to represent the oncoming warmth
and the warm of the Sun.
Though in India the heat is too much,
still people are waiting for this time to come in
and they celebrate it with such a warm heart.
At this time it is said that
they give you this sesame seed and the sugar to eat,
but now you must speak in a sweet manner,
"goad goad bola", means you must speak in a sweet manner.
Speaking in the sweet manner is very important.
Some people think it is smart to speak in a rude manner
or is very intelligent to shout on people,
but no one likes this kind of a personality.
You may be intelligent, you may be very sharp or smart,
maybe on a television people may like to see you,
but not as companions, as friends.
To speak in a very sweet manner
is a sign of good breeding, good culture and fear of God.
Those who fear God will never speak
rudely to another person, because in another person
also the same spirit is shining
and why should we be sharp or angry with another person
who is created by God Almighty as we are created.
So this loving, beautiful relationship
that we have with each other,
after Sahaja Yoga especially,
let us express in talking to each other sweetly.
There are so many ways by which we could be sweet.
There are little, little things if you do,
you can create lot of sweetness,
but you need not a sharp tongue, but a sharp memory.
I try these things many a times.
Once one of the Sahaja Yogi,
who is a very good Sahaja Yogi and an active Sahaja Yogi,
was going in the car with Me
and his knife was stolen by the driver or somebody
and he got very angry with the driver.
I said, "Forget it, you see he is an poor man,
so he has taken it away, doesn't matter, just forget it."
He says, "No, it was because it's a present to me
from somebody who was in Switzerland and
it's a Swiss knife which I was keeping with me.
So I feel sorry that I have lost it."
When I went to Switzerland I bought that kind of a
same knife for him.
When I came, when I gave him,
he didn't have words to say anything.
He said, "Mother, how did You remember?
After such a long time how did you manage
to get this knife?"
I said, "I have a very good memory."
That's the trouble with Me.
The memory is so good that sometimes,
I just don't know,
I may embarrass some people with My memory.
It is that good, I don't forget anything whatsoever.
I, of course, forget all the bad things,
because no use remembering bad things,
no use thinking of them.
Because of forgiveness you can always forget the bad things.
And if you remember the good things
your joy becomes multiplied.
If you try to remember something bad
then your joy goes down.
Every time you see a person try to remember
what good that person has done to you.
What good that person has.
If you have memory for good things
you will have a very nice time.
Now today is the day when you are all leaving India.
Some of you will be leaving day after tomorrow.
Whatever it is,
I have to tell you one thing, that
whatever was possible has been done here, for you people
to give you joy and happiness.
Now when you are going back,
try to remember all that was said to you.
All that was nice.
How people praised you.
How they loved you. How they were kind to you.
How you met some nice people.
What nice experiences you had
but don't brood over things which are worthless.
All right, somebody must have said something harsh to you
or you might have said something harsh to someone,
just forget it.
Try to understand that you are spoiling
your chances of enjoying life.
Nobody is hurt by that so try to be extremely happy
that you have met so many people,
that you have had weddings,
that you have seen so many weddings.
We have had a nice time and every bit of it was
full of joyous vibrations.
Of course, today some of you would be a little unhappy
I can understand that because your spouses are leaving,
somebody's husbands are going away or
somebody's wives are going away.
So I can see some of them
are looking rather miserable about it.
But that's a good thing because it is out of love
and out of attraction for each other,
for enjoying the company of each other.
That's suggestive of something very good to Me
but still I would say that, after all,
you are going to meet each other
and remember all the good things that
you have said to each other,
you have enjoyed with each other and try to keep happy.
Because these days will pass very fast.
In Sahaja Yoga you just forget time, everything,
the time passes so fast and all these things will pass over
and you will be again united with your husbands or wives,
whatever may be the case.
So there is nothing to feel very sad about all these things,
and to keep smiling and laughing,
so when they are departing also,
they should not feel, see your last face full of tears but,
but remember the face of assurance and courage,
that the hope is there,
we are going to meet very soon and
there is nothing to feel very sad about it.
Today is the day to make joy and to enjoy everything
and to feel the blessings of God all around us.
The Sun has come back in His own glory
and we have to wish Him all success in the coming year,
because in this part of Maharashtra
as you know there has been no rain.
There has been problems with them and
we have to wish Him success
so that He can bring forth the rain
and all that is needed out of this solar energy
that we have in this country.
And you have to be beaming like the Sun
when you go back to your countries.
That your countries are not so hot as ours are neither
you have that much of warmth there and you can find
that why people are so warm and so much loving because
we have the Sun with us.
Now you carry the Sun with you and you give them love
and affection and warmth and let them feel that the Sun
has been brought from India by you.
Whenever I have traveled anywhere, in any country,
the Sun used to be there very bright, so they said that,
there is a saying that, when the Indians travel
they carry the Sun with them.
Of course you can't carry the Sun in your pockets
but we must be carrying it in our hearts, the Sun.
That must be the reason that's why
the Sun was shining so well
and everybody came out with their good dresses
and everything was ...were, and were enjoying.
So this is what it is,
that you have to carry the Sun with you
speaking sweetly today and forever to each other
to be friendly, to be helpful, to be kind
because you are yogis,
you are not ordinary people.
You are yogis, you represent that category of people
who are known for their righteousness,
for their goodness and for their compassion and love.
So I wish you all best of luck.
Enjoy your journeys,
enjoy everything and pass this joy
that you have achieved here,
to other people, to other Sahaja Yogis
and to other people who are not even Sahaja Yogis.
May God bless you with that.
Shri Mataji speaks in Marathi.
Today is an auspicious day when
we give sesame seeds
to others and ask them to talk sweetly.
We tell others but it wd be better
to tell it to ourselves also
because it is easier to
tell others to talk sweetly
but: “I’ll talk harshly.”
This habit of ours...
But we´ve created
wrong ideas about ourselves.
We don´t have any idea of the
blessings that God has bestowed upon us.
God has given such a lot of
blessings to us in this country.
In this country people don´t
care much for cleanliness.
In this country there are
different types of germs
and parasites.
I feel that we have all the
parasites of the whole world
in this country. We even
have parasites which
can´t be found anywhere
else in the world. If these parsites
go to the other countries they
won´t survive due to the cold.
Due to the Sun, there
are so many parasites
in this country.
Once a scientist
asked Me, “How is it possible to be alive
overcoming so many parasites
present in your country?”
I replied: “Not only
that people are alive
here but live with joy, happiness
and with a lot of bliss due to this Sun”.
The Sun has
taught us to keep our homes and
also our hearts open.
In England, if you´ve to go out somewhere
then you spend atleast
fifteen min just to put on
the right clothes. As if
to wear
a shield before going out,
otherwise you might catch
a cold and affect your head.
This is the situation there.
You can`t sit out in the open in
England or any other Western country
the way you are sitting here today.
Because of the weather these
countries are very cold.
Even in our country there
are regions, for example
if you go to the cities like
Bhuwali or other side of
Nainital and Dehradun and
very close to the Himalayas, then
you can find the cold
weather same as in other countries
like in England and America.
But in these cold
countries not even birds or
insects can survive.
There are a lot of forests
with beautiful flowers in them.
People tell, it´s a valley of flowers.
with so beautiful flowers,
as if a paradise
on earth, but this
feeling is only for a moment.
It is so cold there, we
can´t even open our eyes
to see that beautiful place.
We´ve to wear spectacles
else our eyes are hurt,
because of the cold.
But in spite of the cold,
those countries have progressed so much.
They have fought against
the nature and the cold climate
and strengthened their countries.
In spite of having a lot of
sun, we haven´t been able
to exploit its advantages.
We neglected the blessing of solar energy.
We have so much solar energy in our country
that if we use it,
we´ll never have a
dearth of (electrical) energy.
Even the cars can run on solar energy.
But the attention of our
politicians in India is
elsewhere and due to this fact,
we can´t exploit the advantages
from the Sun;
it is wasted.
On the contrary we suffer
from it. It is in excess.
If we save it, we can do a lot of work. The
main thing to learn from the Sun
is it´s capacity of giving.
It always gives, only gives.
Does not take anything.
Due to it´s tremendous giving power
we can have rains,
crops and living beings.
If there were no Sun,
we would have nothing.
It is due to it´s power of love
we have been able to reach this state.
thus we have to learn from the Sun is that
we should also develop
the power of giving.
But if we look around us we will find
people who always think,
"How can I save money and
keep it for myself?". Even
if I give money to spend
for some program, some people
still have a tendancy to
save money from that also.
"Who asked you to save?"
"No, we just thought to save".
“But for whom?" "If you´ve
been given to spend it,
why do you want to save?"
Because there is a tendancy
somehow to hold on to
something, to suck the energy of others.
This is the attitude in people
everywhere. If you go to the market,
They tell you, "we´ve raised the prices".
"Why?" "Because others have done it". "But
if the cost of commodities is the same,
why do you raise the (selling) price?"
So the attitude is to suck anyhow.
Even if for a small ceremony, they
tell me, “Shri Mataji you won´t succeed.”
I ask, “Why?” "Because people
are corrupt and eat (grab) money.
Means, I consume food
& they eat money, so we may not get along.
It is such an absurd thing.
Those who are responsible
for the country’s welfare,
who´re the administrators
& on whom the power has
been bestowed by God, even they
don´t get it that we´ve to give.
One has to learn this
from the Sun that we´ve
come (on this Earth)
to give and not to take.
This complete change
from within has to occur.
That passion one has to
have; like your mother has:
"Today my son is coming;
what can I do for him,
what can I cook for him?"
She has that passion.
Shri tries to manage with whatever
little she has; might borrow ingredients
from neighbours if she doesn´t have
and prepares some sweet for you.
She is eager to please you.
Unless and untill we
have this kind of passion,
collective passion from within,
and awaken this kind
of feeling about others,
neither our own nor any
other country can progress.
But we always have the urge to take
things from others,
to plunder or to deceive others.
Because of this urge
our children will suffer,
we will suffer and
we won´t be able to achieve
anything in this country.
In my in-law´s village
to build a lake money
was given by the govt.
in thousands for the purpose.
But the lake was never built.
They said, they had dug a hole but then
they covered it again
since they didn´t find any water.
But in fact the hole was never dug.
So where did all the money go?
They sent it to Switzerland (bank).
So the banks will again borrow from
Switzerland and send
it again to Switzerland.
If the Sun acts this way,
then we won´t survive
even a single day.
If he alone eats (consumes)
everything, what can we eat?
Today we are celebrating the SANKRANTI.
Sankranti means a sort of
Kranti (revolution) by which
we acquire the habit of giving.
Everybody says that we
should have
the habit of giving but most of the
people
believe in donating
something to the priest.
No, not that way.
Or some people preach the art of giving
just to fill their own pockets.
That doesn´t have any meaning.
If you don´t deserve,
why should we donate you?
So the question arises to
whom we should donate.
In fact, in all liberty and
freedom we should see
for ourselves what we
are giving for our country,
our brothers, sisters and our neighbours.
We should not be selfish
but give with all our heart.
So that gives us special joy
which I always enjoy the most.
When we give with all our heart,
the joy we get can´t be compared with any
other joy. And if we want to feel that joy
then only we should celebrate this
SANKRANTI festival. Means our nature
should become like the Sun. He isn´t
conscious about whatever He´s doing.
He does all in AKARMA(without
feeling of doing it) but is
constantly burning himself and
giving you joy, light,
and the essence of living
He nourishes you.
We see Him every day and
many people do Namaskar also,
but just for the sake of
Namaskar
without imbibing his qualities.
We should imbibe his
capacity of giving in our country.
I told you a very small
thing: that every Sahaja yogi
should plant a banyan
tree on the sides of the road.
Why do you need money
for that from the govt?
Just to plant a tree
with a fence around that
doesn´t need much money.
This year let us do that only.
How much does it cost?
Even to smoke bidi (tobaco) costs more.
Try to do this small thing so that
you do atleast something (useful).
Instead, we think how to plunder others,
how to get and save money at others cost.
Because of these tendancies,
our country can never progress.
We didn´t have people like this before.
I can tell you when I was young I saw
only people who believed
in giving and never in taking.
They didn´t like taking. Even
the parents wd ask their
children to return if they
took anything from others.
I still remember in my father´s house
they had made some chairs
and an umbrella, out of silver.
Everybody asked: "why did you make these?"
"When there´re
marriage ceremonies,
people have to hire it so
better we´ve it once for all".
Then it goes on moving from one house
to another. Sometimes some people ask
for it. So they had
to tell them: it´s with
so and so. You´ll have
to pick it up from them.
Eventualy it got lost in that way.
So what I wanted to say,
that was their mentality: that if we´ve
surplus money, what shold be done?
we should invest it for some
collective purpose.
If you want to construct a badminton court,
everybody should be able to play there.
Not that,
only my children will play.
If someone buys a
car, it should be able
to take all the children to school,
so better to buy a big car.
This habit of being collective and
useful to others
one should learn from this Sun.
And today is a special
day when we should take a
vow: "from today
I´ll do something which is
collective". I don´t
understand how people can
eat their food without
thinking about others.
You don´t even worry about your
neighbors. You don´t do anything
for common people. I asked you just
a small thing to plant a tree.
We´ve got so many
sahaj yogis in Maharashtra.
Even if each one plants one tree
and looks after it, that
would be very greatful
to all here. Thus I request you all
to do something collective.
But don´t think how much I
earn or make money out of it
It shouldn´t happen like the
way we give money to the priest.
One should lovingly do
something for the
collective with open heart
and feel the joy out of it.
This should happen.
I don´t want to say
that do everything for free. I never say
that do something for free
for these people from abroad.
Not at all. But these people
have brought so many gifts for you.
Even though I have contributed a lot,
they themselves have
brought so many things
for you.
First I thought that
these were the presents which
I had bought in Rome for you.
But they told me, "No Shri Mataji,
these are the gifts from us".
They felt such a lot of joy
to bring so many things for you.
They don´t even know to
whom these gifts are given.
Here I´m naming &
distributing to all but they
don´t bother, they just leave it to me.
But indians, we´ve a
tendency to think only about our
children, our mother.
Then the mother comes limping on one leg.
I said, "ok".
"She didn´t get nineyards saree".
(S.M.):"I don´t have".
"Ok then, five yards saree will do".
But it is just the opposite with them.
They came with so many things,
it seems they brought two
tons of gifts from abroad.
Even my hands started
paining while distributing them.
What I want to say that
you don´t need to
give anything to them.
They don´t expect anything
from you. But with your behaviour
you should set an example for them,
that: "We also don´t
lag behind in hospitality.
we´re here to serve you when
you come, to welcome you".
What´s the harm in dooing
whatever is possible for us?
It doesn´t cost any money,
nor any hard work. Only, we
should change our mindset.
& if we don´t change
it even in Sahaja Yoga
then I don´t feel that we can
change the entire
humanity with Sahaja Yoga. The
most imp. quality
to give others should be imbibed in us.
In Sahaja Yoga your Kundaliny is
awakened and you realise your spirit.
It´s essence is like that of the Sun
that is of giving.
If you´ve seen one of my photographs,
there is the Sun shining on my heart;
in fact there is a Sun in my heart.
And that´s why I never feel that I
should plunder them.
I don´t understand which part of the brain
this idea comes from,
to plunder them.
This behaviour is very strange.
That should never happen in sahaja yoga.
On the contrary we must think
what we can give or do for others.
Every day try to think some ideas.
In Rahuri itself I´ve
started an organisation
which is named as "SAHAJ STREE SUDHAR"
(Association for women
welfare) or "SAMAJ SUDHAR".
(Society Reform).
Because through Life Eternal Trust
we can´t work for the
welfare of the women.
Thus we had to create this organization
& it´s been registered here.
Everything is done.
People from Canada &
elsewhere are ready to
donate for this organization.
But here I don´nt find anybody
to work for it.
If the local women take it upon themselves
to work for this organisation
then it will work out.
We have acquired a
land and all the facilities
but, "we don´t find time to devote for it.
How can we go to this place?".
These people came from abroad with
money to donate for your organisation.
Help the women emancipation.
Fourteen machines are brought for you.
Try to train them for
something. Can´t you see
women loitering about
wihout doing anything?
Make them work so that they can
earn something out of it and can
prosper. We should try to think about these
things. How can we think
about ourselves only?
So sahaja yogis should know
that selfish attitude
has no scope in Sahaja Yoga.
We should think in
terms of global advantage.
I always say, the lives
of saints [vibhuti (incarnations)]
are for the salvation of the world.
But if it is vice versa,
then finished! It has no meaning.
So now you have become saints
so you should behave like saints
and the first quality
of a saint is giving.
He just gives. I´ve
never heard of a saint plundering anybody.
If a saint thinks of cheating, then
he is no more a saint.
It never comes to his mind. Thus
how much we can give to others,
how much love we can
give, how many people
we can help, all our
attention should be on this.
Nowadays as there are welfare associations
just for election purposes,
we shouldn´t create any such
type of welfare association,
But associations
in which we can
work selflessly like mother´s
NIRVYAJYA (unconditional) love.
Love which has no limits and is endless.
When you give this
kind of love, automatically
you´ll know what is to be done.
Gradualy there should be an improvement.
All sahaja yogis should
contribute to this collective welfare.
We should dedicate
some of our time for it
and
work hard to achieve our goals.
It shouldn´t happen that
“Shri Mataji comes, gives a talk,
& when She goes everything is finished.”
These people (from abroad) have done a lot.
They have started schools and
social welfare.
We should also start something like that.
Sahaja yoga shouldn´t
become just an
association of lazy lumps swimming
in the oean of joy
after realisation. It
shouldn´t happen this way.
We should try to see
how we can help others.
We should open our eyes to look around us
with love and try to see what we can
do for others. I haven´t
been able to move to India yet.
Once I come back to India you´ll see that
I´ll make everyone work.
Thus it´s better to start before.
Sahaja Yoga is not meant
only for sitting and meditating.
For meditating why do you need
Sahaja Yoga? You can go the Himalayas.
If you want to do Sahaja
Yoga living here then
the common people should
be helped by Sahaja Yoga.
But Sahaja Yoga
shouldn´t become like these
modern welfare organizations.
We should accomplish
it with full sincerity
and only then we can say that
we´ve established Sahaja Yoga.
Now I heard a lot of praise for Me.
I heard the songs and it
gave Me a lot of joy and
satisfaction that people
have recognized Me.
But you should remember one thing –
you should work in order to know yourself
otherwise you can´t see yourself
in the mirror.
You should be able to see
what you´ve achieved.
But if you continue same as before,
looking after your household, your children
and if you aren´t able to
work for collective,
then what you´ve achieved
through Sahaja Yoga?
You have ramained where you were.
You have not progressed
at all. Next year when I come,
you should be able to tell me how many
banyan trees you´ve planted.
Secondly, you should be able to
tell me what collective or
social work you´ve done.
If you try to look around,
you´ll definitely be able
to see some collective
work which you can do.
And I´m sure you´ll be
able to do it very well.
It doesn´t need any money
– only you have to decide in your mind.
When I started Sahaja Yoga,
I had given realization to one lady only
and I started without any money.
I didn´t have any support from
the family either.
But due to the dedication of the work &
it´s truthfulness,
it has spread so much.
Now each one of you,
man or woman,
has the responsibility while
introducing Sahaja Yoga to the
general public, to be able
to give them some proof of
general well being. You
needn´t break any law for this.
Neither do anything wrong nor do
anything incorrect.
Only in a proper way just
watch with your eyes open
what you can do for the people,
how you can help the
wellbeing of the people.
And I’m here to give
you all the strength and
energy to do this work.
We don´ need any vote,
nor any money, nothing else.
Just give me a promise that you´ll start
working for the
welfare of the people.
Sometimes when
people start some welfare
work they go round asking for funds.
This´s wrong. We shouldn´t ask for money.
First you should start
some work which
doesn´t need any money.
Everyone feels that without
money we can´t do anything.
You´ve got the powers,
why do you need money?
If somebody is sick or not
well in your neighbourhood
then you can go, visit him
and try to soothe that person.
Instead of that, what I see,
you bring the sick person to Me.
The other day, someone brought
an injured person with
a broken arm to Me.
Any sahaja yogi could´ve
treated him in two min.
but instead, they brought
him to Me & that too
right in the
middle of a program
& asked Me to treat his arm.
You are so many &
all the powers are flowing
through your hands but
you don´t use them.
These people don´t do this. If you are
not able to treat even these small ailments
what is the use of you being
a Sahaja yogi? Someone says,
"my mother is sick, my
father has broken his leg.”
Treat them yourself,
you do have the powers,
atleast try to use them.
Thus you should be able
to help the people happily,
without expecting anything in
return.
You will be able to feel a
lot of joy when you´ve
the feeling that you don´t
do anything but you´re just
an instrument of God
and you are giving
something special in this
world, in this country
and in these families.
Such a big thing, such
a big understanding!
If all of you decide to
work with this feeling then,
you´ll be able to do something for others
& then people will see what Sahaja Yoga is.
Just now people think
that Sahaja Yoga is–
just everybody meditating
together & that’s all.
Even if there´s some problem
in the country, Sahaja yogis
are just sitting in meditation.
One man told Me, “My wife doesn’t cook.”
I asked, “Why?”
He said, “She just meditates.”
I said, “Is it so? But
who told her that?”
First she should cook, for meditation even
five minutes are sufficient.
I´ve given you the power,
to cook well.
Thus one should have the
confidence and the capability of work.
I´m giving you the
powers, assimilate them.
Just to meditate every day isn´t enough.
You´ve to see what wellbeing you
are giving to others. But instead of that,
you always think about your own
wellbeing. "Treat my son, get me a good job
treat my mother,
my father,
come to my house,
do this, do that".
Just imposing your will upon Me
but what about you?
You should remember that
you also have to do something.
“I´ll show Shri Mataji that I’m capable of,
doing something special.”
We should decide this once and for all.
I have an image in front of
My eyes as Shri Gyaneshwara
had described, "BOLTE PIYUSHANCHE SAGAR."
(Words or sayings are
like the oceans of nectar)
Where is it? I want to see it.
Thus on this auspicious
day I give you all
My sweet blessings that
you will help everyone,
look after their wellbeing, treat
everyone with love and talk sweetly
with full of love.
He is saying you should put your hands
like this to say that you are bound by Mother's words.
And we will try to do good to others and
we will be very kind to each other.
I've been telling them that we have to be collective
not among only Sahaja Yogis but with others also.
We should see surroundings, what's wrong where,
how we can help. We have many social obligations
which we have to fulfill.
Now you have reached the stage where you can do that
without forming any social organization which collects money
and have saints and things that kind of a nonsense.
But you can see around yourself who are the needy,
to whom you can help.
And that is how you can really give
a very positive form to Sahaja Yoga.
Marathi
Rahurila
I'll be giving this water to all of you
all the leaders and aslo..
you can take it.
this water is very good for
all diseases of the Mooladhara chakra.